SOAP web service using JAVA SE, Glassfish

WSDL
UDDI
SOAP

Based on contract between producer and consumer which can be used even if source, target technologies are different. It is XML , so interoperable.
Everything based on Annotations. Classes are from javax.ws.* package

@Webservice -> Properties - name, portName, serviceName, targetNamespace
@SOAPBinding -> Two styles a) Document (by default), b) RPC.
@Webmethod
@WebParam
@WebResult

Glassfish provides a WSDL as output if a class is annotated with @Webservice annotation. It also provides a tester class that can be used to verify the output.
Document -> Gives types in wsdl as another schema.

If input and output are complex rather than single data type(Use RPC), it is preferred to use Document style.

We can extract an interface from class with all operations web service is supposed to perform and that now acts as End Point Interface. But the current class still need to have annotation as @Webservice and give property to annotation - endpointInterface = "package.interfacename" and specicy serviceName, portName in current class rather than interface. Reason is an endpoint interface can have multiple implementations and because of that reason the service name and port name is being picked from the service implementation.﻿

JAXB - Java Architecture for XML binding

Use @XmlRootElement at top of class which needs to be root element. Eg: Properties -> name
Use @XmlType at top of class so that some other properties can be set. Eg:  Properties -> propOrder

@XmlElement annotation can be used at a member level so that some other properties can be set specific to that member. Eg: Properties -> name, changes the way how member is displayed in wsdl.

If we use JAXB annotations on a class, there is a need to initialize a no-args constructor for the class else JAXB cannot initialize the class or create new instance.

When we declare an exception in our class, it gets into WSDL as Fault message. It gives information about exception that is set to throw. Information given in getFaultInfo() method of exception class is displayed in FaultInfo section of output.

Glassfish tester page returns stacktrace error message instead of xml based error response. So use tools like SOAP UI so that request and response are in XML formats.

Can access Web service using Web service explorer tool that is present as part of Eclipse.

Without deploying web service to a server, we can test them if just JDK is present. Create a simple Java class with main method and use "Endpoint" class from javax.xml.ws package.

Endpoint.publish("http://localhost:port/xxxxx", new ServiceImplClass());

We get a single thread if we run web service with this but needs to be changed to multithreading if multiple calls need to be made(This is enough to do testing while in dev phase). But with GlassFish, we can make multiple calls to web service.

Metro is a reference implementation that follows JAX WS standards and that actually publishes the web service. Since Metro is bundled with GlassFish, if our code follows JAX-WS standards, we are able to run webservice. 

Metro is also bundled with JDK and hence, without publishing to a server we can run a web service.
------------------------------
If there is an existing SOAP ws that we want to consume, we can use wsimport <<WSDL name>> to generate stubs which are domain classes, service classes, port methods out of it. wsimport comes along with JDK.

Code that is generated using wsimport might not compile . This may be due to type names and other options specified by us. Check binding files option of wsimport which solves this issue. This helps to override some defaults.

wsimport has multiple options

-p <package>
-d <dir>
-keep
-s <dir>
-b binding_file.xml wsdl


----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------
SOAP Message:

A SOAP message is an ordinary XML document containing the following elements:

An Envelope element that identifies the XML document as a SOAP message
A Header element that contains header information
A Body element that contains call and response information
A Fault element containing errors and status information

A SOAP message MUST be encoded using XML
A SOAP message MUST use the SOAP Envelope namespace
A SOAP message MUST use the SOAP Encoding namespace
A SOAP message must NOT contain a DTD reference
A SOAP message must NOT contain XML Processing Instructions

The required SOAP Envelope element is the root element of a SOAP message. This element defines the XML document as a SOAP message.

The encodingStyle attribute is used to define the data types used in the document. This attribute may appear on any SOAP element, and applies to the element's contents and all child elements. A SOAP message has no default encoding.

SOAP defines three attributes in the default namespace. These attributes are: mustUnderstand, actor, and encodingStyle.

The attributes defined in the SOAP Header defines how a recipient should process the SOAP message. Header can be namespace qualified.

The SOAP actor attribute is used to address the Header element to a specific endpoint. 

The required SOAP Body element contains the actual SOAP message intended for the ultimate endpoint of the message. Immediate child elements of the SOAP Body element may be namespace-qualified.

The optional SOAP Fault element holds errors and status information for a SOAP message.

SOAP bindings are mechanisms which allow SOAP messages to be effectively exchanged using a transport protocol.

The Content-Type header for a SOAP request and response defines the MIME type for the message and the character encoding (optional) used for the XML body of the request or response. The Content-Length header for a SOAP request and response specifies the number of bytes in the body of the request or response.